<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration set forth by the Protestants in France shewing the lamentable distresse and calamities that they of Bearn in France are fallen into, by meanes of the oppression and wrong done vnto them, in regard of their profession of the reformed religion. With all the troubles which happened vnto them since the beginning of the edicts sent out against them by the French king vntill this time. Together with the rest of their proceedings, vntill this present moneth of Iuly. 1621.</title>
            <author>Eglises réformées de France.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A72087</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11303.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11303</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118170</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99898421</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99898421</idno>
            <idno type="VID">177857</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A72087)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177857)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1236:14, 2064:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration set forth by the Protestants in France shewing the lamentable distresse and calamities that they of Bearn in France are fallen into, by meanes of the oppression and wrong done vnto them, in regard of their profession of the reformed religion. With all the troubles which happened vnto them since the beginning of the edicts sent out against them by the French king vntill this time. Together with the rest of their proceedings, vntill this present moneth of Iuly. 1621.</title>
                  <author>Eglises réformées de France.</author>
                  <author>Bern (Switzerland : Canton) aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[E. Allde],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Rochell [i.e. London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>French original not traced.</note>
                  <note>Actual place of publication and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Huguenots --  France --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177857:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177857:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> DECLARATION SET FORTH BY THE Proteſtants in France; ſhewing the <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable diſtreſſe and calamities that they</hi> of Bearn in France are fallen into, by meanes of the oppreſſion and wrong done vnto them, in regard of their profeſſion of the reformed Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With all the troubles which happened vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them ſince the beginning of the Edicts ſent out againſt</hi> them by the French King <hi>vntill this time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with the reſt of their procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, vntill this preſent moneth of Iuly. 1621.</p>
            <p>Printed at Rochell 1621.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb facs="tcp:177857:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:177857:2"/>
            <head>A Declaration, ſet forth by the Proteſtants <hi>in France.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O haue and endure calamities, and not to feele them, is a mortall infirmitie, ſeeing that feeling is an affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Life. To feele aduerſities, and dare not complaine, is a cruell reſpect, &amp; an enemye to nature, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that griefe &amp; ſorow is eaſed by teares, and aſſwaged by complaints; we endure calamities at this preſent, and yet haue not hearts of Braſſe or Steele to feele our owne miſeries, nor yet ſo ſoft nor faynt, that we dare not complaine: Seeing then that all other remedies at this preſent are taken from vs, let vs fill our eyes with teares, the Ayre with our ſighes, and this Paper with the true recitall of the miſeries that we endure; And ſo at the leaſt we ſhall reape that contentment to make our griefe knowne to our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theren, &amp; letting them vnderſtand our troubles, we ſhall moue them to compaſſion with vs, it being a iuſt thing, that as we are vnited togither by one ſelfe-ſame Religion, and hated for one cauſe, we ſhould be touched with one ſelfe-ſame and the like feeling.</p>
            <p>It is plaine and manifeſt to all the Realme of France, that there was a Sentence giuen, &amp; Iudgement ſent forth vpon the ſame, for the attachment of the ſpirituall Land in the country of Bearn (ſo much ſpoken of) which Sentence and Decree was giuen, without hearing or permitting thoſe of the reformed Churches of this Soueraigntie, againſt all order of Iuſtice, to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:177857:3"/>be heard ſpeake in their onwe cauſe: And there are but fewe men, to whom it is not known, that for the ſpace of 51. yeares, our Miniſters (the Colledge and Gariſon of Nauerreux) had their maintenance and entertainment onely, out of the ſame. No man likewiſe is ignorant of the iuſt Complaints that our Churches haue made, not onely againſt that Decree and Edict made thereupon, but alſo againſt an other Edict cald the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply; wherby we were ſent out of the Country, to ſeeke that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment. All thoſe that haue vnderſtood our cauſe, may eaſilye iudge of the equity of our Complaints, ſeeing that the ſoueraigne Court of Bearn, by two Decrees made at the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of thoſe Edicts (and of a Commiſſion) had declared, That there was no cauſe to iuſtifie the ſaid Edicts, which oght to be acknowledged for iuſt, ſeeing that the generall Aſſembly of the Churches of the Religion in France, holden at Loudun with ſo great affection &amp; zeale, craued and purſued the reuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of that Arreſt and Edicts: The ſaid complaints &amp; pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits likewiſe were iuſt, for that the King (by the aduice of his Counſell) granted the ſaid Aſſembly ſeauen monthes time, to begin, from the ſeauenth of Aprill laſt, wherein the Churches of Bearn ſhould be heard, and might make their complaints &amp; declarations vnto his Maieſtie, touching the ſaid Decree and Edicts. And let vs adde hereunto, for the better Inſtruction &amp; ſatiſfaction of thoſe that know it not, That the generall Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the reformed Churches in France, during that time, ſeeking and ſoliciting the ſaid reuocation, Anſwer was giuen them by the Kings Counſell, that they muſt ſtay the comming of the Churches of Bearn, And his Maieſtie him ſelfe being at Bourdeaux, wrote vnto the Iudges of the Parliament of Pau, that he did not diſlike, that the ſaid Churches ſhould haue the aduantage of the ſaid moneths, in their ſauour graunted vnto the ſaid generall Aſſembly, The Tenor of which Letter folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in this Diſcourſe: To diſtruſt the Royall worde of a King,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:177857:3"/>no man could doe it without offending his Maieſtie: to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, that during the time graunted, his Maieſtie would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the verification of his Edicts, had bene a crime meriting great puniſhment; neuertheles, beholde we beſeech you, what hapned vnto vs during the ſaid time.</p>
            <p>The King hauing appeaſed the troubles that began to ariſe in the State of France, reſolued to diuert his victorious Armes into Guyenne, and being at Bourdeaux, nothing was ſpoken of in the Court but of Bearn: Bearn was the onely ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of the diſcourſes, and the obiect of the animoſity of thoſe, that long time had practiſed and ſought our ruyne and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe. The Romiſh Prelates kindled thoſe coales, to cauſe a great fire to burſt forth, vſing all the meanes they could to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame the Kings wrath againſt vs, ſpecially employing thoſe meanes that are moſt ordinary with them, that is, ſlaunders &amp; euill wordes, deſcribing vs to be Rebels and I diſobedient, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely ſaying, that all the Country was in Armes, and that we ſpake not of the Kings ſacred perſon, but iniuriouſly and with great deſpight. Theſe impoſtures being continually hangd at the eares of the Miniſters of the State, more and more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing the hatred of the Religion, and the deſire vtterly to extirpe it. And knowing that the execution of the Edict of ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing vpon the Eccleaſticall Lands, would be a meanes to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace and diſhonour the Churches of this Country, &amp; to caſt them into a pittious &amp; lamentable eſtate; and to the contrary raiſe the Romiſh Church to a prodigious greatnes, and the height of riches; did moſt induſtriouſly employe all the artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall meanes &amp; practices that they could deuiſe, to effect their deſignes, and thereby with them to make a hole in the treaſure of worldly dignities, and to play faſt and looſe with them that drew no other breath then that of the earth. The Kings Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell compoſde of Cardinals, Biſhops, and Ieſuites, that were ſure not to ſtop their eares againſt their ſolicitations, but rather
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:177857:4"/>had an inſtreſt in their demaunds, perſwaded the King that it was a meanes to diminiſh his authorities, and that the cauſe was his and not the Biſhops.</p>
            <p>Vpon the report that the King came into Guyenne the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of Pau appointed two Deputies to goe to the King whereſouer he was, and to aſſure his Maieſtie of their moſt humble and obedient ſeruice, which the ſaid Deputies with great dilligence ſpeedily performed, finding the King at Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deaux, where nothing was ſaid vnto them, but onely touching the veryfication of the Edict of the ſenſure of the ſpirituall Lawes, whereby the King had fully reſolued to content the Pope, and to further and aduance the Romiſh Church. And to that end his Maieſtie had already commanded Monſieur <hi>dela Force</hi> Gouernour &amp; Lieutenant Generall of theſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and Monſieur <hi>de Caſaux</hi> chiefe Preſident in the ſayd Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, to repaire to him at <hi>Bourdeaux;</hi> who being come to the Court; they kneeled downe before the King, not onely in their owne names, but alſo in all the names of thoſe of the Country, to renew the aſſurances of their ſubiection, obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and moſt humble fidelitie, who after audience had, he commanded them to returne to Bearn againe, thererin to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the execution of his will and pleaſure, and to cauſe the Edict for the ſeazing vpon the Eccleſiaſticall lands, made in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of the Biſhop of Rome, and that of the ſupply made in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of our Churches to be verified. After them, about the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of October, he ſent a ſecond commiſſion into Bearn by Mounſieur <hi>de la Cheſnay,</hi> to ſolicite the Iudges, and to make them capable of the impreſſions, which the King counſell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to giue them: he threatned them with the comming of the King; aſſuring them, if they refuſe the ſame, he had reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to turne his forces againſt them.</p>
            <p>The Parliament knew not what to reſolue: on the one ſide being abaſhed by his menaces; and a feare to draw vpon the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:177857:4"/>Country a totall and an ineuitable ruyne, knowing that the wrath of a King is death: On the other ſide, conſidering the Kings Edict, finding it to be contrary to ſo many other Edicts, Proclamations and Declarations, made aſwell by his Maieſtie (now raigning) as by the Kings his predeceſſors, contrary to the graunt of the aforeſaid tearmes of ſeauen monthes, made to our Churches, contrarie to the peace and aſſurance of the ſtate, and which is worſt of all: The ruine of the ſayd Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, as bereauing them of the land that were alotted vnto them for the maintenance of their Miniſters, and making them tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butants to the Popes officers. What ſhould they doe, ſhould they breake, and annihilate ſo many Edicts, to iuſtifie, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low one? Should they be conſtrained to diſobay the King, to yeild obedience vnto him? He that in all things ought to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the good of the ſtate and to be a tutor to the people; ſhall he doe a thing that is contrarie to the good of the ſtate; and diſturbe the peoples peace? He that make profeſſion of the true religion, ſhall he be cauſe of the loſſe of his religion? He that was borne in the Church, fed &amp; nouriſhed in her boſome, ſhall he be conſtrained (Oh hard and heauie condition) for ſauing of his owne body to pierce his mother the Churches Breſt?</p>
            <p>At laſt, hauing long waighed this caſe in the ballance of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty, he determined to vſe an indifferent courſe betweene two extreamities, &amp; therevpon ordained, ſeeing it had pleaſed his Maieſtie, by the interceſſion of thoſe of the aſſembly gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall holden in Loudum, to grant his ſubiects of Bearn, making profeſſion of the reformed religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſpace of ſeuen moneths, to preſent their moſt humble ſupplications and declarations, ſeeing alſo that not long before his Maieſtie had vouchſafed to write to the Parliament, that his intent was that the Churches of Bearn ſhould haue the aduantage of the ſaid time, which as the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was not expired, he ordained (I ſay) that humble ſuplicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhold be made vnto the King to beſeech him to hear &amp; giue au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:177857:5"/>vnto the ſaid Churches within a month, whom he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by decree to go thither, within the time that yet reſted vnexpired, to proſtrate themſelues at his feete, to preſent their humble ſupplications and requeſts vnto his Maieſtie, and in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault thereof, the Parliament would binde it ſelfe, to verifie the Edict without moderation or reſeruation, according to his Maieſties commandement. To beare this decree to the King, and to informe him of the equitie thereof; two Counſellors of the ſayd Court of Parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t were deputed. But all they could doe, they could not obtaine the effect of this ſo iuſt a demand: And who would euer haue thought that the King would haue refuſed to heare the moſt humble ſupplications of his faithfull Subiects, deſiting to proſtrate themſelues at his feet in all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, ſeeing alſo that he had ſo ſolemnly promiſed by his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers giuen to the motions made by thoſe of the aſſembly at Loundun, Is not the King as able to will, as puiſſant to holde his worde &amp; to accompliſh his promiſes? Shall we complain, ſurely not of the Kings bountie (ſo iuſt and curteous a Prince) but of the malice of this world and the euill diſpoſitions of the ſpirits of the Court, diſpitefull againſt vs, and reſolute to ſeeke our diſtruction.</p>
            <p>The King hauing heard the Tenor of this Deeree, roughly ſent the Deputies away, and thereupon determined and fully reſolued to goe into Bearne: whereupon, the Parliament being aduertiſed of his deſigne, to appeaſe the Kings wrath, and to diuert the effect of his ſeuere threatnings, determined to verifie his Edict, without moderation or reſtraint whatſoeuer: What ſhould it haue done, ſhould it haue reſiſted a King that came with a wrathfull ſpirit, accompanied with a puiſant &amp; fearfull Army, to abate, caſt downe &amp; breake in pieces, all thoſe that ſhould reſiſt and withſtand? The Edict being iuſtified, the Kings Attourney generall had charge to beare the verification of the ſame to the King, as a teſtimony of our obedience and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:177857:5"/>ſubmiſſion: who found the King all ready on his iourney to Bearn, &amp; ſhewing himſelf before him as he was on the way, he preſented the verificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Edict vnto him, which was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his pleaſure: But he being reſolutely determined to make the Bernois feele the effect and rigor of his wrath, ſtaide not therefore, but went forward. Moſt puiſſant Prince, will not your grace be pleaſed, in ſome meaſure to moderate your wrath? will you not at this preſent ſhew your ſelfe as gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and gentle vnto your Subiects, as you are terrible and redoubted of your enemies? ſhall that Country that hath had the glory to haue borne, nouriſhed in her boſome, and finally giuen France that great <hi>Herculee,</hi> the terror of the world: <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the great your Father, ſooner feele the arrowes of your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, then the effects of your fauour and being preſence?</p>
            <p>The nearer that the King approached to Bearne, the Court of Parliament attended and expected nothing but threatnings againſt this poore Countrey: it was already ordained to the pillage, and thoſe of the religion to the ſlaughter, as an offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to be made to appeaſe the Kings wrath. The papiſticall Edict of the Towne of Morla'as (preſented ſome dangerous accidents againſt vs) who to defend themſelues from the croſſe, marked their houſes with a croſſe; It was againſt the Paſtors particularly that their malice extended, and ſpecially againſt thoſe, who being imployed ſhewed ſome rigor in maintaining the Churches cauſe, all their names were knowne at the Court; they were noted and marked by their faces: on all ſides they were counſelled to flie into Rockes and holes in mountaines and Caues. In the meane time the King entred into the Countrey; accompanied with terror and feare. The Soldiers tooke, pilled, ranſacked, and hardly vſed their Hoſtes, with immeaſurable inſolency, their hands were imployed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout nothing but extortion and violence: Their mouthes ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer opened, but to blaſpheme and curſe God, and to threaten
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:177857:6"/>iniurious bloody perſeeutions, againſt thoſe of the Religion; whom they called rebels, traytors, bougers, olde ſorcerers, and an accurſed race; ſpeaking of nothing but fire, gibbits, and gallowes. They entred forcibly into the Churches, and being therein, brake and caſt downe the Pulpits and ſeates. In the meane time the Papiſts in the Countrey tryumphed and auda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly bragged, whoſe laughters and inſolent behauiours, were, as many arrowes that pierced into the hearts of thoſe of the Religion, ſo much aſtoniſhed for the preſent euils, and the feare of future perils, that it ſeemed, that all thinges conſpired and contributed with enuy to perſwade them, that they had met with another St. <hi>Bartholomewes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The King comming to Pau, would accept of no tryumph, nor ioyfull welcome or receiuing into the Towne; he would ſhow himſelfe to be armed with wrath and diſpleaſure; and like a blazing Starre, which fore-ſheweth the death of ſome great Prince, and the ruyne of an Eſtate. Neuertheleſſe the Conſuls of the Towne went in their Liueries out into the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbs to receiue him; preſenting the keyes of the Towne, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the teſtimony of the obedience and fidelitie of all the inhabitants vnto his Maieſty. The Iudge and others of the Court of Parliament, in ſcarlet robes, fell downe at his feet to yeeld vnto him the aſſurance of ſubiection and fidelity: but the King lookt on them with a countenance full of indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſent them away with this anſwer in fewe words, which entring into their eares, pierced their hearts: Saying, (when you ſerue me better, I will be a good Prince vnto you) and in the meane time while they kneeled at his feet, preſenting their affections and liues in quality of moſt humble, moſt faithfull, and moſt obedient Subiects &amp; ſeruants, ſome ſpake aloude and ſaith, that they were worthy to be hangd vp, as traitors &amp; rebels.</p>
            <p>The Church for her part, and the conſergerie of Pau alſo did their duties, and went to the King being in his chamber, where
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:177857:6"/>kneeling downe before him, &amp; ſpeaking by the mouth of Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Pefarre</hi> one of their Miniſters, they preſented vnto his Maieſty the fidelity of their hearts, conſecrated to his moſt humble ſeruice, as his moſt faithfull ſeruants and ſubiects, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting, that what ſlaunders and calumniations ſoeuer were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed vpon vs, by our euill willers, our Religion commanded vs, to ſerue, honor, obey and reſpect his Maieſty as our King; not only for feare, but ſpecially for Conſcience ſake. The King made him anſwer and ſaid, Serue me well and I will loue you. This contentment was a comfort vnto us, againſt all the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniations, and inſolent ſpeeches vſed againſt vs, that it was reported vnto vs, that by the mouths of the Cardinals and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops that then were preſent, and by the generall conſent of all that heard vs, being no ſmall number: The Church receiued this teſtimony, that our Miniſter had ſpoken worthily and moſt Chriſtianlike.</p>
            <p>While his Maieſty ſtayad in Pau, who is able to rehearſe all the exceſſes committed againſt thoſe of the Religion? If a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter ſpake, he was pointed at with their ſingers; he was reui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and laden with iniuries: how many of them receiued diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, were beaten, and hardly vſed openly in the ſtreets, for making open confeſſion that they profeſſed the reformed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; how many for feare of blowes, were conſtrained to make the ſigne of the croſſe? how many vpon the generall day of Proceſſion were forced with blowes of ſtaues, to kneele downe on the ground to adore the hoſt, which with ſo great pompe was caryed vnder a Cannopy to blinde the common peoples eyes? But what ſhall I ſay, touching the prophanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons committed in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church? The King contrary to that which he had ordained by his anſwers, to the aſſemblies of the Biſhops, gaue the Church of thoſe of the Religion to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, and cauſed Maſſe to be ſaid therein before he went from Pau: Thoſe that firſt entred into it, polluted that place by ſo
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:177857:7"/>many abhominable blaſphemies, that it is mauaile, that the earth did not tremble, &amp; the roofe of the Church fell not down to deſtroy them. But what other thing could they doe, to witneſſe, that from that place they baniſhed the purity of Gods ſeruice, and the inuocation of his name, then by caſting forth ſuch execrable blaſphemies againſt the holy and venerable name of God? being not content therewith, they went vp in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Pulpit, and there ſung impudent and villanous ſongs, and after that filthily eaſed their bodyes therein, caſting the Bible that they found in the Church foure times on the ground: and tare and puld in peeces the table of Gods Commandements that hung on the walles, to witneſſe that they draue the truth of the word of God, and the obſeruations of his commandements out of the Church.</p>
            <p>But this is not all; for I muſt tell you of a moſt abhominable act which deſerueth to bee puniſhed with a thouſand Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and yet the Cardinals and Biſhops that heard thereof, laughed at it, and the diſcourſe made thereof, ſerued in the Court for a matter of ſport and paſtime. One of thoſe abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable raſcals, who in that matter handled the ſacred Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of God, hauing therein read, <hi>Hearken Iſrael,</hi> with horrible blaſphemies cryed out and ſaid, that Iſrael was ſome deuill whom thoſe Buggerers the Hagonites adored: and ſo reiterating both that name and thoſe blaſphemous words, fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly fell vpon the table of thoſe diuine Commandements; and thereupon tooke occaſion to teare them in many peeces. What ſaidſt thou blaſphemous villaine, That Iſraell is the name of a Deuill? Oh little flocke (in the Scriptures called the Iſrael of God) is it poſſible that thy enemies ſhould giue thee the name of Belial? Oh holy Angell of God, haſt thou permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that good Patriarch <hi>Iacob,</hi> to hate the name of Sathan, for the price and reward of his holy and conſtant wraſtling, but rather oh thou the moſt faithfull watchman ouer Iſrael, that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:177857:7"/>neuer ſleepeſt; be thou iealious of the honour of thy name: thou haſt heard this blaſphemous word, and haſt ſeene this prophane villaine, and heard his execrable ſpeaches, that are made a ieſt and laughter to the world. Oh God of vengeance, ſuffer them not long to goe vnpuniſhed, leaſt they ſhould ſay, where is their God?</p>
            <p>To report all the indignities done and offered to thoſe of the Religion, during the time of the Kings being in this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, were a matter that requireth a long ſubiect and great lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; ſome other will ſhortly vndertake to declare them ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally: it ſhall ſuffice for this preſent time to ſhew, that in the ſame time, they fully witneſſed and make knowne what hatred againſt Religion, and what choller againſt thoſe that make profeſſion thereof, they haue conceiued; for their is no word that iſſueth from their mouths, nor action nor motion of their bodies, which tendeth not thereunto, ſo farre, that Monſieur <hi>de Paulo</hi> Preſident of the Court of Parliament in Thoulouſe; ſpeaking to the Earle <hi>de Chambrot,</hi> touching the ſtrange altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that had bin made in Bearne, eapable, as he ſaid, to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the peace and tranquility of France, and to reduce matters to extremities, he made anſwer with a loude voyce (whereby many men of good quallity heard him, ſaying) you deceiue your ſelfe Sir: The Hugonites haue the quarterne ague; They haue bin ſicke a great time, you ſhall ſee other thinges within theſe few dayes, for the King is reſolued to take all their places from them, either by force or willingly: take, and boldly take our Fortreſſes from vs, pull downe the walles of our Townes, beat downe our defences, but yet you cannot bereaue vs of that heauenly retract, and moſt impugnable fortreſſe of the power of God, which appeareth and ſheweth it ſelfe in the conſeruation and defence of his Church.</p>
            <p>All theſe, moſt inſupportable things, haue bin followed and had their courſe with many preiudiciall alterations aſwell in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:177857:8"/>the Church, as in the common Wealth: which might ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently exagerate the loſſe of the Eccleſiaſtical poſſeſſions of the Churches lands, poſſeſſed and inioyed by them for the ſpace of 51. yeares. by good and auaileable Titles, as Edicts, letters Patents, and Decrees of Kings: and now what a pittifull thing it is, that two Biſhops, that liue idlely, in delights &amp; pleaſures of the world, ſhould ſwallow vp and encroach vpon all the poſſeſſions of the Church, and that our Miniſters who inceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly labour in the Miniſtrie of the word of God, to teach the people to feare God, and to obey the King, ſhould be conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, to ſeeke for their maintenance elſe where? what griefe of hart is it, that thoſe that neuer are in reſt, but when they labour and ſtriue againſt vs, ſhould draw &amp; receiue a recompence and reward from vs? that they that make warre againſt vs, ſhould be payd by vs? That wolues ſhould cloth themſelues with the wooll, and nouriſh their bodies with the milke of the flocke? a pittious and lamentable condition; we ſhall ſee two Biſhops abounding in riches, eleuated in Honours &amp; Dignities, and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with delights, march in Royall ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner; but what ſay I, that we ſhall ſee them? yea, and that we ſhall bee conſtrained to contribute the Tenths of our reuenewes to entertaine theſe flaſhes of lightning, and this worldly pompe and magnificence? a hard ſeruitude: we ſhall be compelled to giue our bracelets, our eare-rings, to be molten, to make an Image, and ſhall haue no meanes to contribute any thing towards the building, and preparing of the Tabernacle: and to imploy our goods, for on ornament and beautifying of Babilon, while Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem remaineth deſolate, and her gates burnt down by fire: can wee indure to ſee Idolatry get the vpper hand, and ſeaze vpon our Churches, while for the pure ſeruice of God, and for the Preaching of his word, we haue no other couerture then the Skies, nor receptacle but the mountaines? In our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches where long time, ſo many good and ſacred Pſalmes haue
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:177857:8"/>bin ſung, we ſhall heare a ſtrange and barbarous ſound, and a company of babling Prieſts, exclaime againſt vs, and make our miſeries the ſubiect of their pleaſures?</p>
            <p>The ſtate ought to ſerue for a ſupport and protection of the Church, and thoſe that are aduanced to be Officers in the State, ought to vſe their authority of the conſeruation &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance thereof, our ill willers iealous of the peace and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the ſame, and impatient to ſee it flouriſh and proſper, know that well, and therefore haue effected ſo much, that the Offices and authorities of thoſe of the Religion are taken away from them, and giuen vnto Papiſts; to the end, that the Church holding no more by any branch, may by the leaſt ſhake be borne downe to the ground. The gouernment of <hi>Nauarreux,</hi> hauing bin 51. yeares in the hands of Monſieur <hi>de Sales</hi> a <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman,</hi> on whom the eyes of enuy or hatted neuer ſo ſharpely piercing, could neuer note nor perceiue the leaſt ſhadow what ſoeuer of infidelity towards his Prince, who perceiuing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be very olde, and without Children, certain yeares paſt, obtained the reuerſion of his gouernment for Monſieur <hi>de Laur</hi> his Couſen, who in all his actions ſheweth the foot-ſteps and degrees of a rare &amp; ſingular piety, and in his body beareth the markes of his courage, hauing (in the Kings preſence at the ſiege of Amiens) receiued a ſhot with a Musket in his right ſhoulder, which hath bereft him of the free vſe of his Arme.</p>
            <p>Monſieur <hi>de Sales</hi> ſent him to Bourdeaux, with Monſieur <hi>de la Force,</hi> to aſſure his Maieſty of the continuation of his ſideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, who being at the Court, he found that the enemies of the Religion had diſperſed ſome report abroad that tended to the preiudice of the ſincerity of his affections, which had pierced euen vnto the cares, and almoſt into the thought of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, but comming into the Kings preſence, he diſperſed thoſe ſhadowes, and made the King plainely to ſee and perceiue, that his actions were able to indure the tryall: Whereupon the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:177857:9"/>King, ſheweth him the honour to aſſure him, that he was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of his innocencie, exhorting him, to perſiſt in ſeruing him faithfully, and withall commaunded him to aſſure Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>de Sales</hi> of his fauour and good will. The King approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Frontiers of this Country; Monſieur <hi>de Laur</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented himſelfe once againe vnto him, to reiterate the prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations of his moſt humble and moſt faithfull ſeruice; not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in his owne, but alſo in the name of Monſieur <hi>de Sales,</hi> moſt humbly beſeeching his Maieſtie to beare with his great age, that would not permit him to preſent his body laden with yeares at his graces feet. The King receiuing thoſe words of obedience and fidelity from Monſieur <hi>de Laur,</hi> commaunded him to continue and goe forward in imploying his time for the benefit of his ſeruice. Wherewith hee returned well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented in minde, but vpon the report that was ſpread abroad, of the Kings intent to ſee <hi>Nauarreuz,</hi> he went againe to ſpeake with him at Pau, where Monſieur <hi>de Luines</hi> told him, and the King confirmed it with his owne mouth, that he had no other intent nor meaning but to ſee <hi>Nauarreuz,</hi> and that hee ſhould aſſure Monſieur <hi>de Sales,</hi> that nothing ſhould be altered nor changed in the ſtate of that place. Monſieur <hi>de Laur</hi> aſſuring himſelfe vpon that promiſe, which he thought to be inuiola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, contented himſelfe, and ſought to ſettle and aſſure Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>de Sales</hi> minde and conceite to the contrary, being moued thereunto by diuers aduices giuen him from all places, that his gouernment would be taken from him.</p>
            <p>The King comming to <hi>Nauarreux,</hi> at his entry into the Towne, Monſieur <hi>de Sales</hi> preſented the keyes thereof, and ſpeaking vnto him, ſaid: Sir, it is now aboue fifty yeares that I haue had the honour to be gouernor of this place; God hath giuen me the grace alwaies to haue kept it well, not only in the raigne of the King your Father deceaſed, but alſo in yours: and I am aſſured, that if in your Court there be any of the King
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:177857:9"/>your Fathers old ſeruants; they will witneſſe that his Maieſtie was well contented with my ſeruice, and aſſured himſelfe of my fidelity, I neuer had a better deſire to ſerue, then I haue at this preſent: if your Maieſtie will accept thereof, as I moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beſeech you, and in ſigne of my obedience here are the keyes of the Towne, which I preſent vnto you. The King made him anſwere, that he alwayes was aſſured, and ſtill did aſſure himſelfe more and more of his good ſeruice, willing him to continue and profit in ſeruing him well, and he would be his good Maſter, and acknowledge his ſeruice in time and place when occaſion fell out, commaunding him to giue the keyes of the Towne to Monſieur <hi>le Marquis de la Force</hi> Captaine of his guards, and ſo he did.</p>
            <p>Thoſe pleaſing and agreeable vvords of the King reioyced and comforted Monſieur <hi>de Sales,</hi> and vvith the ſame he began to be ſomewhat comforted: but an houre after the King entred into the Towne, he ſent him word, that he would haue no more of his ſeruice, and gaue the gouernment to Monſieur <hi>de Puyane</hi> a Papiſt, and a Stranger, contrary to the lawes of the Country, whereby Strangers are excluded from thoſe char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; preſently thereupon all the inhabitants were diſarmed, all the Garriſon was diſcharged, that is 120. Souldiers: Their Lieutenant and Enſigne beard, ſixe Captaines, the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, the Controller, the Keeper of the Munition: The Doctor and the Apothicarie all of the religion, and foure Companies of the Regiment of Picardie were brought in vntill Monſieur <hi>de Ruyane</hi> had gathered his compoſed of 300. men, Strangers and Papiſts.</p>
            <p>A moſt pittifull and lamentable deſolation! how could they deale roughlier with that venerable old Gentleman, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the moſt impudent calumniation durſt not accuſe them after 50. yeares and vpwards of his ſeruice, ſhamefully to diſplace him of his gouernment, and thereby layd his gray and weake
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:177857:10"/>age, with ſo ſenſible an affliction: What pittie is it, that he who all his life time had liued in honour and authority, he that by the length and fidelity of his ſeruices, perſwaded himſelfe that he had ſetled that charge in his owne houſe, now in his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter daies, ſhould ſee him ſelfe laden with ſhame, and from ſo eminent a place, reduced to a priuate ſtate, while a ſtranger layd hold on his ſpoiles, and walked like a peacocke vpon the rampers and walls of <hi>Nauarreux,</hi> which his father and he at other times couragiouſly defended, againſt the inuaſion of ſtrangers. It is certaine that the hatred againſt religion is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſiue great, ſeeing that neither the long ſeruice, of that anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Knight, his fidelity without reproch; nor his teares could mollifie the hearts of thoſe that had induced and incited the King, to ſuch a ſeuere reſolution.</p>
            <p>How hard and troubleſome it was to Monſieur <hi>de Laur</hi> that had the reuerſion of that his Vncles gouernment, was recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued therein, and had taken his oath accordingly, that had ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the King commanding with honour aboue 25. yeares ouer a company of the regime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> lamed in the Kings ſeruice, &amp; one that could not be accuſed of infidelity or diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, and for a recompence of all his ſeruices to ſee him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the face of all the Court put from his charge, and made the ſubiect and matter of the ſcoffings, workes and ieſts of our enemies. What griping griefe muſt it needes be, vnto a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous heart, ſencible of the force of honor: poore and deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late inhabitants of the towne, that are all of the religion, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it be one Apoſtate? what comfort and conſolation can mitigate your griefe in this feeling of ſo whot in affliction, but with what words, and mourning weeds, can or may we ſet forth and ſhew that the deplorable ſtate and miſerable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of ſix ſcore Souldiers, moſt of them inhabitants of the Towne; hauing wiues and children, and ſuch as for the moſt part ſucceeded their fathers, whoſe fidelity was manifeſt in the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:177857:10"/>defence of the Towne aſſiged by the Kings enemies? What griefe is it, at this day to ſee them, (without any offence by them committed) diſpoſſeſſed of their places, and diſarmed, and thereby with their wiues &amp; children, brought into ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full pouerty? What burning words might their hearts feele, on the one ſide, to ſee ſtrangers in their houſes brag and braue it out in their armes, &amp; on the other to heare the ſighes and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall complaints of their wiues &amp; children, ready to famiſh? But by what counſell was it done, that our ill willers ſeeke (by making vs loſe this place) to giue vs ſo great a ſubiect com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint? haue not we defended the ſame with the price of our blood, againſt the audatious enterpriſe of the Papiſts, that had driuen Queene <hi>Ioane</hi> out of the Countrie, and by treaſon, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, and reuolting, had gotten all the reſt of this ſtate into their hands? Is it not we, who in recompence of our fidelity, haue poſſeſſed the ſame 60. yeares vnder the Kings ſeruice? Theſe Titles onely were ſufficient and authentique ſeeing they were grounded vpon ſo long a poſſeſſion, ſigned and ſealed with the fidelity and blood of our fathers: and yet this is not all. By the Edict of Nantes it was agreed, that all the places and Garriſons, which were in poſſeſſion of thoſe of the Religion, and not in time to come to be taken from them, and at the ſame time more were giuen them, which after that by many Edicts and Declarations, hath bin confirmed, after that our Churches by the Kings permiſſion, were vnited with thoſe of France, as all the world knoweth; this graunt made by the Edict of Nantes in fauour of the Churches of France, was inlarged in our ſauour by the expreſſe Declaration made by his Maieſtie to the ſupplication preſented by the laſt generall aſſembly held in Rochell; who then would bee ſo obſtinate to doubt whether <hi>Nauarreux</hi> ſo long time holden by vs, in the time of peace, and many yeares before, ſhould not ſtill be kept by vs? What manner of malice is this?
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:177857:11"/>who would maintaine and affirme that it could be taken away from vs, without ouerthrowing of ſo many Edicts, and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, which ought to be firme and inuiolable?</p>
            <p>But now againe ſee how farre they proceed to the ſupreame degree of ſtubbornneſſe and malice, and yet after all that, the moſt bitterreſt perſons muſt holde their tongues, and make no anſwer. The King and his Counſell, knowing that out of the Eccleſiaſticall lands of the Churches or Miniſters Colledge and Garriſon of <hi>Nauarreux</hi> and other charges were maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned &amp; vpholden, ordained by his Decree, that another meanes ſhould be aſſigned vnto vs, for the ſupplying therof, and name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the entertainment of the Garriſon of Nauarreux, which afterward was more expreſly declared in the Edict of ſupply; verified in the Parliament of Pau. What more formall procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding could be deſired then this Edict, which was made in our fauour: then this Edict I ſay, which was onely a meanes for our aſſurance? his Maieſty there aſſigned a meanes for the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of Nauarreux; was not that a witneſſe confirmable to ſo many other Edicts and declaritions, to ſhew that this place ought not to be taken away from vs? Puiſſant King, is it poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that within 4. dayes after the verification of this Edict, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſo many other reaſons, and ſo many other Edicts, that ought to aſſure this place vnto vs: you would take it away from vs? Alas, we haue ſaid it, and are againe conſtrained to reiterate the ſame; pardon vs noble Prince, it is not againſt your royall Maieſty, that our clamours and complaints are made, but againſt the rage and malice of our enemies, which haue done you that wrong, not to permit your promiſes to be inuiolable. Hauing taken Nauarreux from vs, they began to turne the State vpſide downe, and therein to make alterations preiudiciall to the Religion: Garriſons were put into all the Townes, to oppreſſe the liberty of the Countrey, beſides the 4. Companies that are in Nauarreux, in Orthes they put 6. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:177857:11"/>of the regiment of Picardie: in Sanueterre 4. Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the regiment of Champaigne: as many in Oloron of the ſame regiment: and a company of light Horſemen in Nay. Who can ſufficiently declare the great exceſſes and diſorders which thoſe people vndertake in a Countrey, where they are as it were animated by the hope of pillage? Who can without horror tell and ſpeake of the horrible blaſphemies that they belch forth againſt God, and the ieſts and ſcornfull brauadoes which they vomit out of their mouths againſt thoſe of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion? what a ſeruitude it is to liue like ſlaues at home in our owne houſes, and as ſtrangers in the Towne? to ſee our ſtreets full of Corcelets, Pikes and Muskatiers; our meanes, and our liues, in the power of the enemies of our Religion; ready, if God did not reſtraine their impetuoſitie by his prouidence: aſſaile vs, and to put their tyrannous intents in execution.</p>
            <p>All the Countrey concerning Martiall gouernment is diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into 6. parts, which are called Parſans: euery Parſan alwaies had a Captaine that commanded ouer the Souldiers vnder the Kings Lieutenant, moſt ancient Officers; and as it were ordained at the firſt beginning of the State: all thoſe 6. Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines were of the Religion, but what fell out? Enuy could not endure that, that remnant of authoritie ſhould continue in the hands of thoſe of the religion; but rather to weaken them all together, and onely to let them goe and ſcape away with their liues, the ſayd 6. Captaines were diſcharged, without any crime or offence impoſed vpon them, and in their places, there was a new Officer made in the Countrie, that is, a Prouoſt Marſhall with certaine Archers to attend him; and that Office giuen to a Papiſt: What an alteration of affaires is this, To ſuppreſſe the auncient Officers, and to make new, onely to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance the Papiſts, and to raiſe them to a formall greatnes, and to imbace thoſe of the religion, and reduce them to a pittifull and lamentable condition?</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:177857:12"/>
            <p> And further, Monſieur <hi>de Bernac</hi> the chiefe Baron of Bearn, (whoſe aunceſters haue made themſelues famous, in reſpect of their ſincere affection, and loyalty to the Kings ſeruice, and the conſeruation of the Countries liberty,) had a grant in poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, from father to ſonne of the chiefe Precedence in the State: But enuy could not endure that a moſt affectioned fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily to the religion, ſhould be in poſſeſſion of that dignity, and therefore ſought to diſpoſſeſſe him thereof, to inueſt the Biſhops with the ſame; and the better to bring their deſiring to effect, a bruit was ſpread abroad in the Court, that it was not good for Monſieur <hi>de Bernac</hi> to ſtay in Pau, and that if he preſented him ſelfe, he ſhould ſerue for an offering to redeeme and recompence the diſobedience of Bearn: aduice was giuen him from all places, by men of greateſt quality in the Court, that he was appointed to be an example, and an abaſhment to the rebells: he chuſing rather to looſe his eſtate, then his head in Court, reſolued to keepe himſelfe ſecretly in one of his hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and in his abſence, the Biſhops were inſtabled, without any contradiction, in the Precedence of the States, and by that meanes, they had places in the Counſell or Parliament next to the Preſidents, and free voyces therein to Iudge of all affaires, ſpecially of thoſe of the religion, although one of the Biſhops had a Couſin that ſate in the ſame Parliament, and that by the law of the Country, the Vncle and the Couſin cannot be Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in one cauſe and company. But when there is any thing to be done that may diſaduantage thoſe of the religion, there is no law which they will not violate, nor cuſtome which they care not to breake.</p>
            <p>But this is not all, Bearn is vnited vnto France, and by this Vnion the whole eſtare thereof is turned vpſide downeward: We haue two kinds of lawes, the one is the lawe of the Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne, which may be altered, changed or diſanulled as occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions fall out: the other is the Lawes of the Soueraignetie,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:177857:12"/>whereby the Prince is aduanced to the Soueraigne eſtate, and are as it were the Articles and cauſes of the contract made betwene the Soueraigne and the Countrie. Thoſe are inuio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable, and cannot be changed, vnleſſe the ſtate be changed, as being the props whereupon it holy ſtayeth and dependeth. The principalleſt of thoſe lawes being that which bindeth the Soueraigne to maintaine the ſtate in the Title of Soueraigne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and to defend the ſame from allienaton, and tranſporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion elſe where. Now by incorporating Bearn with France, the Title of Soueraignetie is taken from it, and carried elſe where, ſeeing that the King endoweth the Crowne of France there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and by conſequent ouerthroweth the eſtate, by the which intruſion an infinite number of miſchiefes are introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. By the ſame meanes <hi>Nauarre</hi> is ioyned to Bearn, making the Chancerie of <hi>Nauarre</hi> and the Counſell of Pau one Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, by that coniunction to introduce a great number of Papiſts into the body thereof, and ſo much the more to wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken thoſe of the religion, Monſieur <hi>de Leſcun</hi> the Kings Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, would neuer conſent vnto the verification of the Kings Edict touching the Spiritull liuings, but ſtill in the Countrie, in the Court, and in the generall aſſembly did maintaine Gods cauſe, and the Churches right with an inuincible and impene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable vigure and conſtancie, he was hated in the Court, and diligently ſought for, and being not found, he was ſummoned to appeare within twice 24. houres, and failing therein, he was prohibited from executing his charges Moſt braue and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous wraſtler, receiue, I pray thee, this prohibition for an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable reputation, and a glorious marke of thy incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble zeale for the conſeruation of the Church, and in the meane time expect moſt greene Garlands of Laurell, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall Crowne from him, whoſe cauſe thou haſt defended with ſo great conſtancy.</p>
            <p>And you poore and deſolate Churches, which in times paſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:177857:13"/>were like to the land of Goſhen; onely light, while all the Countrey about it was obſcure and darke, and which at this preſent perceiue and behold darkneſſe to get the vpperhand and to preuaile againſt you, to extinguiſh our light, you that haue ſeene the purity of Gods ſeruice planted &amp; reeſtabliſhed in enery place, and Idolatry wholy baniſhed out of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey; and now behold it to be ſpread abroad in all the quarters thereof, to ouerwhelme both the Townes and fields, and to build her neſt in your Churches, &amp; already behold ſquadrons of wormes and graſhoppers riſe out of the bottomleſſe pit of hell, to gather your grapes and mowe your fields, in danger of prohibition not to enter into the houſe of God: reioyce and comfort your ſelues, God at this time calleth you to endure perſecutions, why are you abaſhed and aſtoniſhed thereat? it is your condition, it is the liuery of your head and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, whoſe head being Crowned with Thornes, why ſhould the Church dreame of dignities, &amp; earthly Crownes? you ſee the world riſe vp againſt you: Why ſhould you be diſmayed? it is the ordinarie courſe thereof, it is the enemy of the truth of the Goſpell, which is not of this world but of heauen: an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of the Church, which hath withdrawne it ſelfe from the world, to be tranſported &amp; planted in an other Territorie and place of aboad: your places of defence are taken from you, and are not you lodged in the cloſet of the Soueraigne God, and vnder the ſhadow of the wings of the moſt Mighty? and who can pull you out from thence? is that Fortreſſe to be bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red? is it to be taken by men? The liuing deſtined and appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for your Miniſters are taken from you. And hee that in times paſt commanded the Crowes to be Puruoirs and victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allers for the Prophet <hi>Elias,</hi> he that commanded the oyle in the pitcher not to waſt; and the oyle in the glaſſe not to decay or waxe nought, is not he at this day the ſame God? ſhould his arme be ſhortned that he cannot, or the bowels of his mercy
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:177857:13"/>ſhut vp, that hee will not, haue a care of his Church, and prouide food for his Miniſters? you haue the honour to ſuffer perſecution for righteouſnes ſake, although your enemies ſeeke to imblemiſh the ſame with the Title of rebellion and diſobedience: but where doe the effects, much leſſe the proofes of this rebellion appeare? can they obiect, that you did euer at any time conſpire againſt the Kings ſacred perſon, or attempted any thing againſt his State? that the murtherers of Kinges, (infernall furies of hell) were found or came out from you? that your Miniſters did euer goe vp into their pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits, to proclaime warre, to kindle a reuolt, or to ſowe ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in your hearts? can you be reproched, that you are bound by oath of fidelity and obedience to any other, but vnto the King your Soueraigne? that you acknowledge any ſuperiour power in the world, that can put downe or tranſport his Crowne to any other? haue your Miniſters bookes bin con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to be burnt, as free of falſehood, and deteſtable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, tending to the ſubuertion of Soueraigne powers, and the riſing vp of Subiects againſt their Princes, as the bookes of thoſe that defame and ſlander you by iniuries, and violently purſue you, haue bin? then where is the rebellion and diſobedience, that is improprietated vnto you? It is, (ſay they) becauſe you did withſtand the verification of the Kings Edict, and thereupon they exclaime, and crie out, ſaying, what audaciouſneſſe is this, what an attempt worthy of death is this? What conſolation and comfort haue you, when you ſee and perceiue that they can not accuſe you, but onely by changing the names of things, and by calling that rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, which is nothing but obedience.</p>
            <p>The King hauing giuen the Eccleſiaſticall liuings to the Biſhops, you could neuer obtaine that fauour to be heard by the Kings Counſell, it being inſtantly ſought for and deſired; anſwer was made, that you ſhould be fully heard before the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:177857:14"/>Iudges, to whom the King would ſend his Edict or Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions: You preſented your ſelues before thoſe Iudges, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect and humility, you deſired to be maintained in your poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of 51. yeares, grounded vpon Edicts, Decrees, and letters Patents of the King your Soueraigne. Is it cald rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion with honor to ſolicite your cauſe to the Iudges appointed by the King, and to whom he ſent you to be heard? rebellion to aske and demaund the obſeruation of the Kings Edicts, and execution of his promiſes? What Title will they giue to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion and diſobedience, if reſpectiue and humble requeſts and ſolicitations are qualified with the name of diſobedience and rebellion? An ingenious age, wherein the names of things are changed, thereby afterward to haue the meanes to change and peruert all thinges.</p>
            <p>And you Brethren, that by one ſelfe ſame band of Faith, and Religion are vnited, and ſtrictly bound vnto vs: Behold in this ſorowfull ſpectacle what hath bin done, and what more they will doe vnto you: Conſider our calamities therein, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you are members of the ſame body, behold your owne therein: Make your ſelues ſenſible of our miſeries, helpe vs to finde ſome remedies, either by your moſt humble prayers vnto God, that he will be pleaſed to appeaſe his iuſt wrath and indignation inflamed againſt vs, becauſe of our ſinnes, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulnes, or elſe by your ſupplications to our good King, to be admitted and reſtored to our firſt eſtate, or by your good aſſiſtance againſt thoſe, that doe nothing elſe but labour vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to root out and deſtroy vs, by theſe chollerous alterations.</p>
            <p>In the meane time, God graunt that theſe ſtrange alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, be not the cauſes of other as dangerous, and ominous al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations. God graunt, that ſo often, ſtriking againſt the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our patience, they doe not make ſome ſparkles flie out, and that of thoſe ſparkles ſome great ſide ſhould chance to burſt forth: But before all thinges, God graunt that our good
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:177857:14"/>and debonarie King may be liuely touched with the pure zeale of his houſe, to the end that thinking vpon the greatneſſe of the miſchiefes, that he hath bin counſelled to doe vnto vs, he will ſhew himſelfe to be our reſtorer, and the nouriſher of our Churches: And for our parts, attending that time, and happy motion, of changing, rechanging, and of turning all thinges vpſide downward, wee are fully reſolued neuer to change, our affections vnto God, as Chriſtians, nor to the willes nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, not to honour the King as his faithfull Subiects: But ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as we pray vnto God, to ſtrengthen our patience, that it may not breake vnder the burthen of ſo many calamities, that are procured vnto vs, ſo wee beſeech him to proſper the King, and to giue him long and many dayes, a flouriſhing Empire, and faithfull Subiects.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="decree">
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:177857:15"/>
            <head>BY THE KING, SOVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lord of Bearn.</head>
            <p>LOuing friends and our truſty ſeruants, wee are certified that you haue ſent vnto vs for your Deputies, Meſſieurs <hi>de Gillot,</hi> and <hi>de Lendreſſe</hi> to make your duties known, and to certifie vs of your fidelities without any further charge committed vnto them, although Monſieur <hi>de Cauſaus</hi> chiefe Preſident, gaue you to vnderſtand, that it was our pleaſure that you ſhould ſend ſome of your Deputies to ſpeake with vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout our Edict touching the Spirituall reuenewes, to receiue our commandments, and to yeild vs an account of things paſt, grounding this doubt vpon this, that by the ſayd Monſieur <hi>de Caſaus</hi> letter it ſeemed that your deputation was referred vnto that with thoſe of the religion. P. R. of our Soueraignetie are to make. And although you haue nothing at all to doe with them, and that it is free for them, to take that occaſion, which the time that we haue granted yeilds vnto them; and for that it tendeth to the good of our affaires and ſeruice, the quietnes of the Countrey, that our intents and pleaſure ſhould forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with be made knowne vnto you: for theſe cauſes, we will, and command you, that forthwith, and without any delay, you no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate and ſend ſome of your company vnto vs, to receiue thoſe orders touching the Spiritual liuings, that we will giue vnto them, without depending vpon the deputation of the ſaid Meſſieurs <hi>de Gillot</hi> and <hi>de Lendreſſe,</hi> your duties to obſerue our Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandments binde you thereunto, faile not therein, for ſuch is our pleaſure. Giuen in <hi>Burdeaux,</hi> the 21. of February. 1621.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:177857:15"/>
            <closer>
               <signed>Signed, LOVIS. And ſomewhat lower, DELOMENIS.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>And belowe to our louing friends and faithfull ſeruants of our Counſell in the Soueraigne Courts of Bearn.</p>
               <p>This letter being receiued by the Parliament of Pau: The Decree following, word for word tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into French, was thereupon made.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="order">
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:177857:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Counſell Chambers aſſembled-together, hauing ſeene the requeſts of the reformed Churches of this Countrie, and the Kings letter ſent to the Counſell, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring date the 22. of Nouember, laſt paſt; importing, that it is free for thoſe of the reformed religion to take aduantage of the time, that was giuen them, agreeing with that which before had bin granted to the aſſembly in Loudun. It is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed, That before all things his Maieſtie ſhall moſt humbly be intreated, to giue audience vnto the moſt humble ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and declarations of the ſayd Churches, willing the ſaid Churches, to preſent themſelues vnto his Maieſtie, before the ſaid time be expired, which being expired, and for not doing it, we will proceed to the regiſtring and publiſhing of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict, according to the contents of the Commiſſion, bearing date the 10. of September laſt. And to that end Meſſieurs <hi>du Four</hi> and <hi>de Marca</hi> are appointed Deputies preſently to goe to <hi>Bourdeaux</hi> or any other place, where the King ſhall be.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giuen in Pau, <date>the laſt of Ianuary. 1621.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
